Guide to the Rutherford Montgomery Papers 1931-1973
Special Collections and University Archives, University of Oregon Libraries
Rutherford Montgomery papers
1931-1973
Ax 352
Special Collections and University Archives, University of Oregon Libraries 1299 University of Oregon Eugene, Oregon, 97403-1299 (541) 346-3068 spcarref@uoregon.edu
25.75 linear feet 19 containers
The collection of Rutherford Montgomery includes manuscripts (book length, short story and anthology), published works, correspondence, miscellaneous items (such as speeches, screenplays and screeplay ideas for television and movies), tearsheets, illustrations, scrapbooks, articles, other writings, third party manuscripts, photographs and several other materials that represent Montgomery's career as an author and his career at Walt Disney Studios.
18 containers
Montgomery, Rutherford George, 1896-
Box 2-3, 5-18
Package 1
Box 4
Box 1
Biographical/Historical note
Rutherford George Montgomery (April 12, 1894-July 3, 1985) was born in Straubville, North Dakota to George Y. and Matilda (Proctor) Montgomery. He married Eunice Opal Kirks on February 14, 1930. They had three children: Earl, Polly Montgomery Hecathorn and Marylin Montgomery Fitch. Montgomery attended school at Colorado Agricultural College, at the Western State College of Colorado and the University of Nebraska. He loved flying and the outdoor life. During his life he was a member of the Society of authors, Western Writers of America and Writers Guild of America West.
During his career, Montgomery was a teacher at Hot Springs Elementary School in Hot Springs, Wyoming from 1915 to 1917. From 1917 to 1919 he served in the U.S. Army Air Corps. When he left the service he went back into education as a teacher and principal at Delta County High Schools in Cedar Ridge, Colorado from 1921 to 1924. He then served as principal at Montrose County Junior High School in Montrose, Colorado from 1924 to 1928. Later, for the state of Colorado Montgomery served as Gunnison county judge from 1931 to 1936 and as budget commissioner from 1932 to 1938. Following ths Montgomery spent several years in the literary world, as a freelance writer of children's books from 1939 on. He was a ghost writer for the Dick Tracy series from 1941 to 1946 then became a teacher of creative writing at Los Gatos, California from 1955 to 1957 before going to the Walt Disney Studios in Burbank, California as a writer from 1958 to 1962.
This collection contains a variety of contents ranging from manuscripts to published works to correspondence and a variety of other items. This collection includes tearsheets, articles, screenplays and screenplay ideas.
Collection is organized into the following series:
Correspondence
Manuscripts
Miscellaneous
Addenda 1
Addenda 2
Addenda 3
Addenda 4
Addenda 5
Addenda 6
Addenda 7
Addenda 8
Addenda 9
Addenda 10
Collection is open to the public.
Collection must be used in Special Collections University Archives Reading Room.
There is a collection of Rutherford Montgomery papers at the University of Southern Mississippi, William David McCain Library. NIDS# 4.47.106.
Montgomery, Rutherford George, 1896---Correspondence; Montgomery, Rutherford George, 1896-
Walt Disney Productions
Authors, American--20th century; Children's literature, American--Authorship; Screenwriters--United States
Children and Youth; Literature
Book illustrations; Photographs; Scenarios; Scrapbooks.; Screenplays; Speeches; Tear sheets
- Correspondence, Series
  - Outgoing correspondence, Subseries
    - Outgoing correspondence, 1931-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Incoming correspondence, Subseries
    - A-M, 1933-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - N-Z, 1933-1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - A-Z, 1939-1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Jacob Bates Abbott, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Caxton Printers, Ltd., 1936-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Board of Christian Education, 1939-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Boys Today, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Derrydale Press, 1938-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Doubleday and Co., Inc., 1948-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Grosset and Dunlap, Inc., 1939-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Henry Holt and Co. Inc., 1939-1961 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Houghton Mifflin Co., 1938-1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lenniger Literary Agency, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - David McKay Co., 1936-1946 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Julian Messner, Inc., 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Geo. A. Pflaum, Pub., 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Joseph T. Shaw, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Regarding State Budget Commission, 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - U.S. Air Force, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Western Writers of America, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Westminster Press, 1943-1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Whitman Publishing Co., 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Whitman Publishing Co., 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Willis Kingsley Wing, Author's Representative, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - World Publishing Co., 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Manuscripts, Series
  - Booklength, Subseries
    - Amikuk (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Beaver Water (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Beaver Water (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Capture of the West Wind (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Claim Jumpers of Marble Canyon (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - The Defiant Heart (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - The Defiant Heart (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Kent Barstow Aboard the Dyna-Soar (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Kent Barstow and the Commando Flight (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Kent Barstow and the Commando Flight (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Kent Barstow and the Commando Flight (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Kent Barstow and the Commando Flight (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Kent Barstow on a B-70 Mission (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Kent Barstow, Spaceman (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Kent Barstow, Spaceman (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Kent Barstow, Spaceman (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - A Kinkajou on the Town (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - A Kinkajou on the Town (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - McNulty's Holiday (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Mr. Jim (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Mr. Jim (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Mr. Jim (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Mr. Jim (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - See Catch (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Shag of Pine Valley (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - The Silver Hills (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Snowman (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Snowman (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Snowman (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - The Stubborn One (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - The Stubborn One (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - White Mountaineer (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Short Stories, Subseries
    - A-Z (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Scripts and Scenarios, Subseries
    - Cougar (Walt Disney Productions) (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - El Blanco, Legend of the White Stallion (Walt Disney Productions) (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Miscellaneous, Series
  - Materials and Memorabilia, Subseries
    - Working Notes (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Collected Manuscript (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Reviews and Promotions (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Addenda 1, Series
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Wild Animals As I Know Them (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, Subseries
    - General correspondence (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Brandt and Brandt (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Caxton Printers (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Doubleday, Doran and Co. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Dresser, Davis (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Halliday and McCloy (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Dresser, Davis (cont.) (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Dresser Davis: Contracts (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Kline, Otis A. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Lenniger Literary Agency (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Serial Publication (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Shaw, Joseph T. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Fan letters (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Royalty Reports (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - The P.F. Volland Co. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - 2 Scrapbooks of letters (Box 3)
    - Outgoing correspondence (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Incoming correspondence, 1956-1969 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Addenda 2, Series
  - Film Scripts and Scenarios, Subseries
    - Basic Seance (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Beaver Water (Box 4)
    - Dark Interlude (Two Versions) (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - The Defiant Heart (Box 4)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Ghost Town Gold (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Untitled Proofs (Box 4)
    - Kent Barstow Aboard the Dyna-Soar (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Kent Barstow On a B-70 Mission (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - McNulty's Holiday (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Missile Away (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Snowman (Box 4)
    - Tom Pittman, USAF (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Addenda 3, Series
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - All About Beavers (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - At the Foot of Sleepy Cat (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - At the Foot of Sleepy Cat (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - BoBus (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Croppy's Journey (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - The End of the Rainbow (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Ghost Town Gold (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Ghost Town in Carbon Canyon (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Ice Blink (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - In Your Hands (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Into the Groove (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Jerome Kildee Builds a House (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Jerome Kildee's Pilgrimage (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - A Kinkajou on the Town (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Little Tim's Raccoon (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Monte the Bear (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - McGonnigle's Lake (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Midnight (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Pekan the Shadow (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Side by Side (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Snowman (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - The Stubborn One (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Tim's Mountain (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Whitetail (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, Subseries
    - Short Stories (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - WWA Anthology (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Untitled (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Research (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Research (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 6 books and other miscellaneous loose items (Box 6)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Amikuk (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Beaver Water (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Black Powder Empire (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Comanche Trail (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mountain Man (Box 7)
    - Posted Water (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Snowman (Box 7)
- Addenda 4, Series
  - Outgoing correspondence, Subseries
    - Letters Sent (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Incoming correspondence, Subseries
    - Letters Received (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Caxton Printers (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Doubleday and Co. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Duell, Sloan and Pearce (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Meredith Press (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - World Publishing Co. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Writers Guild of America (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Walt Disney Productions (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Caxton Printers (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Barthold, Fles (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Meredith Press- Duell Sloan and Pearce (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Incoming correspondence (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - World Publishing Co. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Outgoing correspondence, Subseries
    - Outgoing correspondence (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Addenda 5, Series
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Bear by the Tail (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - El Blanco (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Broken Trails (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Claim Jumpers of Marble Canyon (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Cougar (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Folly Mountain Gold (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - The Invasion of Carbon Canyon (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Ghost Town in Carbon Canyon (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - The Golden Stallion (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - The Golden Stallion's Mystery Feud (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - The Golden Stallion to the Rescue (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - In Happy Hollow (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Into the Groove (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Joe Meek, Mountain Man (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Kent Barstow and the Dyna Soar Mission (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Kent Barstow, Secret Agent (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Klepty (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - The Living Wilderness (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - The Living Wilderness (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - McGonnigle's Lake (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - McNulty's Holiday (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Maverick Mountain (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Mountain Maid (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Oddessy of an Otter (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Posted Water (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Rufus (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Red Runs the River (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - SAC World Series (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - See Catch (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Sex Isn't Everything (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - The Shadow Strikes (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Smoky Trail (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Snow Man (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - The Stubborn One (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - The Vanishing Herds (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - The Weary Land (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Weecha, The Racoon (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Short Fiction (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Outlines, Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Tear sheets (Box 9, Folder 26)
- Addenda 6, Series
  - Outgoing correspondence, Subseries
    - Outgoing correspondence (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Incoming correspondence, Subseries
    - Incoming correspondence (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Fan letters (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Addenda 7, Series
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Dick's Blue Streak (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Dolphins As They Are (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - The Golden Stallion on the Adventure Trail (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Pocket Money (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, Subseries
    - Magazines (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Royalties (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Royalties (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Royalties (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Addenda 8, Series
  - Correspondence, 1950-1973; Subseries
    - Correspondence (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Fan Mail (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Flash the Teenage Otter (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Golden Stallion and the Mysterious Feud (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - The Hoofbeats of Sinful Sam (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Into the Groove (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Jack Knapp, Hero of the Teslin Trail (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Jeff and the Jaguarundi (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Jerome Kildee Builds a House (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Mystery Has Craighead (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - The Mystery of the Old Quarry (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Night Ride (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Klepty (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Pekan the Shadow (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - The Shadowed Hills (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - The Shadowed Hills (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Yosemite (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Published Animal Stories (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Tear Sheets (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - SAC Series (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, Subseries
    - Notes and General Research (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Publicity/ Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Scrapbook of Rejections (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Speaking Engagements, 1950-1972 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Wilderness photographs (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - All That Glitters (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Death Has Yellow Eyes (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Death Has Yellow Eyes (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Hill Ranch (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Hill Ranch (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Hill Ranch (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - The Mystery of Crystal Canyon (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - The Mystery of Crystal Canyon (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Seecatchie (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Seecatchie (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Seecatchie (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Seecatchie (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Treasure at Craghead (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Treasure at Craghead (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Yellow Eyes (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Untitled (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous Leaves (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Manuscripts by Other Authors, Subseries
    - Olde English by Robert Wilson (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Addenda 9, Series
  - Correspondence, Subseries
    - Outgoing (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Incoming (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - Robert Carlisle (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Eunice Montgomery (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Bobus (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - The Cats Have Shared (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - The Golden Stallion's Rival (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Hockey Champ (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - The Invasion of Carbon Canyon (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - Mission Intruder (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - The Shadowed Hills (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Carcajou Illustrations (Box 12a)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Shiny on Your Side (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Song Dog of the Dawn (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Survival in a Cat's World (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Weary Land (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Yosemite (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Screenplays (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, Subseries
    - Fan Mail and Drawings (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Contracts, Royalty Payments, etc. (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Photos, Certificates, Awards and Memorabilia (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Writer's Guild (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Two books by Al Avery (Box 13)
- Addenda 10, Series
  - Outgoing correspondence, Subseries
    - 1943-1960 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1961-73 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - A-Car (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Caxton Printers (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Ch-D (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - E-Fi (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Fles, Barthold (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Fo-Go (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Gr-I (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - J-K (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - L-Lee (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Lenninger (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Leu-Ly (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - M (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - N (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - O-P (Box 14, Folder 16)
    - R-S (Box 14, Folder 17)
    - T-U (Box 14, Folder 18)
    - W (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Z (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Amikuk 1 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Amikuk 2 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Big Red (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Catch a Sea Lion (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Choppy's Journey 1 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Choppy's Journey 2 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Choppy's Journey 3 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Comanche Trail (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Corey's Monster (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Danger Flight (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Disaster Canyon (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Dolphin on the Loose (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Ghost Town Gold (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - The Golden Stallion (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - The Hills are Home (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Jet Navigator (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Jungle Boy #1 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Jungle Boy #2 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Kilgee House (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Kit (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Klepty (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Little Tim's Racoon (Box 15, Folder 18)
    - Missile Army (Box 15, Folder 19)
    - Mister Jim (Box 15, Folder 20)
    - Mystery of the Turquoise Frog (Box 15, Folder 21)
    - Old Grizzly (Box 15, Folder 22)
    - Pocket Monkey (Box 15, Folder 23)
    - Posted Water (Box 15, Folder 24)
    - Prisoner in the Circle (Box 15, Folder 25)
    - Rufus (Box 15, Folder 26)
    - Rufus (Box 15, Folder 27)
    - Shadowed Hills (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Shadowed Hills (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Shadowed Hills (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Shorty (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Side by Side (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - The Silver Mug (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Skippy (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Show Man (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Survival in a Cat's World (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Survival in a Cat's World (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Trail Dust (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Tracy Twins South of the Border (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Treasure at Craghead (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - West of Muddy River (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - West of Muddy River (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Yellow Eyes (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Black Bear (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Brown Clown (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Come to Mountain (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Cougar (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Dark Interlude (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Disney Material (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - El Blanco (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Face in the Window (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Flash (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Flash (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Flash (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - High Button (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Man Against the House (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Matter of Rank (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Matter of Rank (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - The Pack (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - SAC Series (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Sancho (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Trooper's Three (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Up in Henry's Room (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Uranium (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Weecha (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Yellow Eyes (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Almost a Man (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Bring in Your Ship (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Chickaree (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - The Door (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Eye Witness (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Fragile Tenancy (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - The Hungry Jaguar (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - An Inch of Time (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - It Pays to Be Lazy (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - King (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Not to Be a Frosh (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - The Road (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Under the Mountain (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Welcome Home (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - The White Killer (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Angles on Writing the Western Juvenile (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - King Sized Rat (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - One Grizzly (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Uranium Widow (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - Hockey Champ (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - Kinkajpu (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - Ways of the Wild (Box 17, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous, Subseries
    - Untitled Narrative (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Story Outlines (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Pitman Material (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Outline for "The Story" (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Biographical Material (Box 17, Folder 37)
  - Third Party Manuscripts, Subseries
    - Aley, Al. Little Lost Burro (Box 17, Folder 38)
    - Barker, Elliot. Four in a Day (Box 17, Folder 39)
    - Barker, Elsa. Line Camp Christmas (Box 17, Folder 40)
    - Barker, O.S. The Button and the Bronc (Box 17, Folder 41)
    - Bunch, Charlie. Men Are That Way (Box 17, Folder 42)
    - Charman, John. Navajo Common Law (Box 17, Folder 43)
    - Croy, Harlan. Homer the Pig. (Box 17, Folder 44)
    - Dashew, Martha. Diaper a Weigh (Box 17, Folder 45)
    - Dashew, Martha. Diaper a Weigh (Box 17, Folder 46)
    - Dashew, Martha. Diaper a Weigh (Box 17, Folder 47)
    - Dashew, Stanley. Skipper of the Constellation (Box 17, Folder 48)
    - Ellis, Ray G. Thundercloud (Box 17, Folder 49)
    - Halacy, Jr. D.S. Brong For a Greenhorn (Box 17, Folder 50)
    - Lane, Fred (Box 17, Folder 51)
    - Marx, S. (Box 17, Folder 52)
    - McCornack (Box 17, Folder 53)
    - McGowan (Box 17, Folder 54)
    - Mellinger (Box 17, Folder 55)
    - Nelson, A. (Box 17, Folder 56)
    - Taylor, S.W. (Box 17, Folder 57)
    - Thurston, J.H. (Box 17, Folder 58)
    - Vance, W. (Box 17, Folder 59)
    - Warren, Beatrice (Box 17, Folder 60)
  - Miscellaneous, Subseries
    - Photographs (Box 17, Folder 61)
    - News clippings: Biographical material (Box 17, Folder 62)
    - News clippings and reviews of Montgomery books (Box 17, Folder 63)
    - Tear sheets (Box 17, Folder 64)
    - Artwork and miscellaneous loose items (Box 17)